Let me share with you today an original discovery.
دعوني أشارككم اليوم اكتشاف جديد
But I want to tell it to you the way it really happened --
ولكنني أود أن أقصه عليكم كما حدث في الواقع
not the way I present it in a scientific meeting,
ليس بالطريقة التي أعرضه بها في اجتماع علمي
or the way you'd read it in a scientific paper.
أو الطريقة التي تقرؤونها في الأوراق العلمية
It's a story about beyond biomimetics,
إنها قصة عن ما بعد التقليد الحيوي
to something I'm calling biomutualism.
إلى ما أسميه التبادل الحيوي
I define that as an association between biology and another discipline,
وأعرف ذلك بالترابط بين علم الأحياء وإنضباط آخر.
where each discipline reciprocally advances the other,
حيث كل تبادل منضبط يخدم الآخر
but where the collective discoveries that emerge are beyond any single field.
ولكن مجمل الاكتشافات الناتجة أكبر من أي مجال مفرد.
Now, in terms of biomimetics,
الآن، في ما يخص التقليد الحيوي
as human technologies take on more of the characteristics of nature,
بينما تأخذ التقنيات البشرية صفات أكثر من خصائص الطبيعة،
nature becomes a much more useful teacher.
الطبيعة تصبح معلم أكثرفائدة.
Engineering can be inspired by biology
الهندسة يمكن أن تستلهم من علوم الاحياء
by using its principles and analogies when they're advantageous,
باستخدام مبادئها ومصطلحاتها حين تكون مفيدة
but then integrating that with the best human engineering,
ثم بعد ذلك دمجها مع أفضل الهندسة البشرية,
ultimately to make something actually better than nature.
في النهاية لعمل شئ في الواقع أفضل من الطبيعي.
Now, being a biologist, I was very curious about this.
الآن، كوني أحيائي، فقد كنت فضوليا جدا بهذا الخصوص
These are gecko toes.
هذه أصابع الوزغة
And we wondered how they use these bizarre toes
وقد تسائلنا عن كيفية استخدامهم لهذه الأصابع الغريبة
to climb up a wall so quickly.
لتسلق الجدران بهذه السرعة
We discovered it. And what we found was
وقد اكتشفناه. وما وجدناه
that they have leaf-like structures on their toes,
انه لهاهياكل شبيهة بالريش علي الاصابع,
with millions of tiny hairs that look like a rug,
بها ملايين الشعيرات الدقيقة والتي تبدو كالسجادة
and each of those hairs has the worst case of split-ends possible:
وكل واحدة من هذه الشعيرات بها أسواء حالات الانقسام الطرفي،
about 100 to 1000 split ends that are nano-size.
حوالي 100 إلى 1000 انقسام طرفي، بحجم النانو
And the individual has 2 billion of these nano-size split ends.
والفرد لديه 2 بليون من هذه الانقسامات الطرفية بحجم النانو
They don't stick by Velcro or suction or glue.
إنها لا تلتصق بالشفط أو الغراء
They actually stick by intermolecular forces alone,
في الواقع انها تلتصق بقوي بين الجزيئات فقط.
van der Waals forces.
قوي فان دير فالس
And I'm really pleased to report to you today
وأنا سعيد جدا لأبلغكم اليوم
that the first synthetic self-cleaning, dry adhesive has been made.
أن أول لاصق صناعي جاف ذاتي التنظيف قد صنع.
From the simplest version in nature, one branch,
من أبسط نسخة في الطبيعة، فرع واحد
my engineering collaborator, Ron Fearing, at Berkeley,
معاوني الهندسي، رون فيرنج، في بيركلي
had made the first synthetic version.
صنع أول نسخة اصطناعية
And so has my other incredible collaborator,
وكذلك معاوني الرائع الآخر
Mark Cutkosky, at Stanford --
مارك كوتكوسكي، في ستانفورد
he made much larger hairs than the gecko,
فقد صنع شعيرات أكبر بكثير من الوزغة
but used the same general principles.
ولكنها تستخدم نفس المبادئ العامة
And here is its first test.
وهذا هو اختباره الأول
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's Kellar Autumn, my former Ph.D. student,
هذا كيلار أوتومن، طالبي السابق للدكتوراه
professor now at Lewis and Clark,
الآن بروفيسور في لويس آند كلارك
literally giving his first-born child up for this test.
يقدم طفله الأول حرفيا لهذا الاختبار
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
More recently, this happened.
وفي الآونة الأخيرة، حدث هذا
Man: This the first time someone has actually climbed with it.
الرجل: هذه أول مرة يتسلق بها شخص في الواقع
Narrator: Lynn Verinsky, a professional climber,
المعلق: لينن فيرينسكي، متسلقة محترفة
who appeared to be brimming with confidence.
والتي تبدو فياضة بالثقة
Lynn Verinsky: Honestly, it's going to be perfectly safe. It will be perfectly safe.
لينن فيرينسكي: بصراحة، سيكون ذلك آمن تماما. سيكون آمن تماما
Man: How do you know?
الرجل: كيف تعلمين ذلك؟
Lynn Verinsky: Because of liability insurance. (Laughter)
لينن فيرينسكي: بسبب التأمين
Narrator: With a mattress below and attached to a safety rope,
المعلق: بوجود مرتبة بالأسفل ومربوطة بحبل أمان
Lynn began her 60-foot ascent.
بدئت لينن تسلق الـ 60 قدم
Lynn made it to the top in a perfect pairing
وصلت لينن إلى القمة بتزاوج ممتاز بين
of Hollywood and science.
هوليوود والعلم
Man: So you're the first human being to officially emulate a gecko.
الرجل: إذا فأنت أول بشر يقلد الوزغة رسميا
Lynn Verinsky: Ha! Wow. And what a privilege that has been.
لينن فيرينسكي: ها! واو. وأي شرف كان لك
Robert Full: That's what she did on rough surfaces.
روبيرت فُل: هذا ما قامت به على الأسطح الخشنة
But she actually used these on smooth surfaces --
ولكنها استخدمت هذه على الأسطح الناعمة في الواقع
two of them -- to climb up, and pull herself up.
زوج منها، لتتسلق، ولترفع نفسها
And you can try this in the lobby,
ويمكنكم تجربتها في البهو
and look at the gecko-inspired material.
والنظر إلى المواد المستوحاة من الوزغة
Now the problem with the robots doing this
المشكلة الآن لتقوم الروبوتات بذلك
is that they can't get unstuck,
هو أنهم لا يستطيعون فك التثبيت
with the material.
بهذه المادة
This is the gecko's solution. They actually peel their toes away
وهذا هو حل الوزغة. إنهم في الواقع يقشرون أصابعهم
from the surface, at high rates,
من السطح، بسرعة عالية
as they run up the wall.
بينما يركضون إلى أعلى الحائط
Well I'm really excited today to show you
وأنا متحمس جدا لأطلعكم اليوم
the newest version of a robot, Stickybot,
على أحدث نماذج روبوت، ستيكي بوت
using a new hierarchical dry adhesive.
يستخدم اللاصق الجاف الهرمي
Here is the actual robot.
هذا هو الروبوت الحقيقي.
And here is what it does.
وهذا ما يقوم بفعله
And if you look,
ولو نظرتم
you can see that it uses
سترون أنه يستخدم
the toe peeling,
تقشير الأصابع
just like the gecko does.
كما تفعل الوزغة
If we can show some of the video, you can see it climbing up the wall.
ولنستطيع عرض جزء من المقطع، يمكنكم رؤيته يتسلق الحائط
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
There it is.
ها هو ذا
And now it can go on other surfaces because of the new adhesive
والآن يمكنه العمل على أسطح أخرى بسبب اللاصق الجديد
that the Stanford group was able to do
الذي تمكنت مجموعة ستانفورد من صنعه
in designing this incredible robot.
لتصميم هذا الروبوت المذهل
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Oh. One thing I want to point out is, look at Stickybot.
آه. أود التنويه إلى، انظر إلى ستيكي بوت
You see something on it. It's not just to look like a gecko.
سترون عليه شيئا. ليس فقط لجعله شبه الوزغة
It has a tail. And just when you think you've figured out nature,
لديه ذيل. فما أن تعتقد أنك قد فهمت الطبيعة
this kind of thing happens.
يحدث مثل هذا الأمر
The engineers told us, for the climbing robots,
لقد أخبرنا المهندسون، عن الروبوت المتسلق
that, if they don't have a tail,
أنه لو لم يكن له ذيل
they fall off the wall.
سيسقط من الجدار
So what they did was they asked us
فما فعلوه هو سؤالنا
an important question.
سؤالا مهما
They said, "Well, it kind of looks like a tail."
قالوا "لإنه يبدو كذيل"
Even though we put a passive bar there.
ولو أننا وضعنا عامودا غير فعال
"Do animals use their tails when they climb up walls?"
هل تستخدم الحيوانات ذيلها وهي تتسلق الجدران؟
What they were doing was returning the favor,
ما فعلوه هو رد الجميل
by giving us a hypothesis to test,
بإعطائنا فرضية لنختبرها
in biology, that we wouldn't have thought of.
في الأحياء، التي لم نكن لنفكر فيها
So of course, in reality, we were then panicked,
فبالطبع، في الواقع، أصبحنا متوترين
being the biologists, and we should know this already.
كوننا ،علماء احياء،ومن المفترض أننا نعرف ذلك سلفا
We said, "Well, what do tails do?"
فقلنا "حسنا، ما الذي يقوم به الذيل"؟
Well we know that tails store fat, for example.
فمثلا، نحن نعرف أن الذيل يخزن الدهون
We know that you can grab onto things with them.
نعلم أنه يمكنه الإمساك بالأشياء
And perhaps it is most well known
وربما كان مشهورا
that they provide static balance.
بإعطاء التوازن عند السكون
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It can also act as a counterbalance.
يمكنه أن يستخدم كوزن معاكس
So watch this kangaroo.
فشاهدو هذا الكنغر
See that tail? That's incredible!
أرئيتم ذلك الذيل
Marc Raibert built a Uniroo hopping robot.
قام مارك رايبرت بصناعة روبوت أحادي للقفز
And it was unstable without its tail.
وقد كان غير متزن بدون ذيله
Now mostly tails limit maneuverability,
في الغالب يحد الذيل من القدرة على المناورة
like this human inside this dinosaur suit.
مثل هذا البشري داخل لبس الديناصور
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
My colleagues actually went on to test this limitation,
قام زملائي بقياس هذه المحدودية
by increasing the moment of inertia of a student, so they had a tail,
عن طريق زيادة لحظة القصور الذاتي لطالب، ليصبح له ذيل
and running them through and obstacle course,
وجعله يجري في بين العقبات
and found a decrement in performance,
ووجدوا تدني في الأداء
like you'd predict.
كما تتوقعون
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But of course, this is a passive tail.
ولكن بالطبع، هذا ذيل ساكن
And you can also have active tails.
كما يمكنكم الحصول على ذيل فعال
And when I went back to research this, I realized
وحين عدت لبحث ذلك، أتضج لي
that one of the great TED moments in the past,
أن أحد لحظات تيد الماضية الرائعة
from Nathan,
من ناثان
we've talked about an active tail.
تحدثنا عن ذيل فعال
Video: Myhrvold thinks tail-cracking dinosaurs
الفيديو: ميهرفولد يعتقد أن ديناصورات الذيل اللاسع
were interested in love, not war.
كانوا مهتمين بالحب، وليس الحرب
Robert Full: He talked about the tail being a whip for communication.
روبيرت فُل: تحدث عن الذيل كونه سوط للتواصل
It can also be used in defense.
كما يمكن استخدامه للدفاع
Pretty powerful.
ذيقوي جدا
So we then went back and looked at the animal.
فآخذنا رجعة وتأملنا في الحيوان.
And we ran it up a surface.
وجعلناه يصعد سطحا
But this time what we did is we put a slippery patch
ولكن هذه المرة أضفنا رقعة زلقة
that you see in yellow there.
التي ترونها بالأصفر هناك
And watch on the right what the animal is doing with its tail
وشاهدو على اليمين، ما يفعله الحيوان بذيله
when it slips. This is slowed down 10 times.
حين ينزلق. لقد بطأنا هذا للعشر
So here is normal speed.
هذه السرعة الطبيعية
And watch it now slip,
وشاهدوه الآن ينزلق
and see what it does with its tail.
وشاهدو ما يفعله بذيله
It has an active tail that functions as a fifth leg,
لديه ذيل فعال يعمل كرجل خامسة
and it contributes to stability.
وتساهم في التوازن
If you make it slip a huge amount, this is what we discovered.
إذا جعلناه ينزلق مسافة كبيرة، هذا ما اكتشفناه
This is incredible.
هذا غير معقول.
The engineers had a really good idea.
كانت لدى المهندسين فكرة رائعة
And then of course we wondered,
وبالطبع تسائلنا
okay, they have an active tail, but let's picture them.
حسنا، لديهم ذيل فعال، ولكن دعونا نتصورهم
They're climbing up a wall, or a tree.
إنهم يتسلقون جدارا، أو شجرة
And they get to the top and let's say there's some leaves there.
ويصلون إلى القمة ولنفترض أن هناك ورقة
And what would happen if they climbed on the underside of that leaf,
فما الذي يحدث لو أنهم تسلقوا إلى أسفل الورقة
and there was some wind, or we shook it?
وهنا كانت بعض الرياح، أو نحن هززناها؟
And we did that experiment, that you see here.
وقمنا بتلك التجربة، والتي ترونها هنا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And this is what we discovered.
وهذا ما اكتشفناه
Now that's real time. You can't see anything.
الآن هذا بالسرعة الحقيقية. لايمكنكم رؤية شئ.
But there it is slowed down.
والان هنا بالبطئ.
What we discovered was the world's fastest air-righting response.
ما اكتشفناه كان أسرع ردة استقامة هوائية في العالم
For those of you who remember your physics, that's a zero-angular-momentum
لمن منكم يذكر الفيزياء، هذه زخم زاوية الصفر
righting response. But it's like a cat.
ردة فعل للتصحيح. لكنها مثل الهرة
You know, cats falling. Cats do this. They twist their bodies.
كما تعلمون، الهرر تسقط. الهرر تقوم بهذا. يلوون أجسادهم
But geckos do it better.
ولكن الوزغ أفضل
And they do it with their tail.
ويقومون به بذلهم
So they do it with this active tail as they swing around.
فهم يقومون بذلك بهذا الذيل الفعال بينما يلتفون
And then they always land in the sort of superman skydiving posture.
ويهبطون دوما بوضع مثل سوبرمان
Okay, now we wondered, if we were right,
حسنا، الآن تسائلنا، إذا كنا محقين
we should be able to test this in a physical model, in a robot.
ينبغي أن نكون قادرين على اختبار فعلي لهذا النموذج، في روبوت
So for TED we actually built a robot,
لذا بنينا في الواقع روبوت لتيد
over there, a prototype, with the tail.
هناك، نموذج بالذيل
And we're going to attempt the first air-righting response
وسنجرب أول استقامة هوائية
in a tail, with a robot.
بذيل على روبوت
If we could have the lights on it.
لو سلطتنا ضؤ عليه.
Okay, there it goes.
حسنا، ها هو ذا
And show the video.
وأعرض المقطع
There it is.
ها هو ذا
And it works just like it does in the animal.
إنه يعمل تماما كما في الحيوانات
So all you need is a swing of the tail to right yourself.
إذا فكل ما تحتاجه هو هزة من الذيل لتصحح نفسك
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now, of course, we were normally frightened
الآن، بالطبع، نحن خائفون
because the animal has no gliding adaptations,
لأن الحيوان غير مكيف للتحليق
so we thought, "Oh that's okay. We'll put it in a vertical wind tunnel.
هذا ما اعتقدناه "لا عليكم. سنضعه في نفق رياح رأسي
We'll blow the air up, we'll give it a landing target, a tree trunk,
ستهب الرياح إلى أعلى، وسنحدد له هدف للهبوط، جذع شجرة
just outside the plexi-glass enclosure, and see what it does.
خارج الزجاج مباشرة، ونرى ما سيفعله
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So we did. And here is what it does.
وذلك ما فعلناه. وهذا ما فعله
So the wind is coming from the bottom. This is slowed down 10 times.
فالرياح تأتي من الأسفل. هذه عشر السرعة
It does an equilibrium glide. Highly controlled.
إنه يحلق بتوازن. بسيطرة عالية
This is sort of incredible. But actually it's quite beautiful,
هذا مدهش نوعا ما. ولكنه جميل في الواقع
when you take a picture of it.
عندما تلتقط صورة له.
And it's better than that, it -- just in the slide -- maneuvers in mid-air.
بل هو أفضل من ذلك، فهو يوجه نفسه في الجو
And the way it does it, is it takes its tail
وطريقته في ذلك، يأخذ ذيله
and it swings it one way to yaw left, and it swings its other way to yaw right.
ويؤرجحه لجهة ليعرج يسرة، ويؤرجحه للجهة الأخرى ليعرج يمنة
So we can maneuver this way.
فنستطيع التوجيه بهذه الطريقة
And then -- we had to film this several times to believe this --
ومن ثم -- إحتجنا أن نصور هذا عدة مرات لنصدقه
it also does this. Watch this.
إنه أيضا يقوم بهذا. شاهدوا هذا
It oscillates its tail up and down like a dolphin.
إنه يذبذب ذيله للأعلى والأسفل مثل الدولفين
It can actually swim through the air.
إنه في الواقع يستطيع السباحة في الهواء
But watch its front legs. Can you see what they are doing?
ولكن شاهدوا أرجله الأمامية. هل تستطيعون رؤية ما تفعله
What does that mean for the origin of flapping flight?
ما الذي يعنيه ذلك لأصول الطيران بالرفرفة
Maybe it's evolved from coming down from trees,
ربما تطور من السقوط من الأشجار
and trying to control a glide.
ومحاولة التحكم بالتحليق
Stay tuned for that.
تابعونا بهذا الخصوص
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So then we wondered, "Can they actually maneuver with this?"
فتسائلنا بعد ذلك "هل يستطيعون بالفعل المناورة بهذه الطريقة"؟
So there is the landing target. Could they steer towards it
فهذا هدف الهبوط. هل يستطيعون التوجه نحوه
with these capabilities? Here it is in the wind tunnel.
مع هذه القدرات؟ ها هو ذا في نفق الرياح
And it certainly looks like it.
وهو بالتأكيد يبدو كذلك
You can see it even better from down on top.
يمكنكم ملاحظة ذلك بشكل أفضل من المنظر العلوي
Watch the animal.
شاهدو الحيوان
Definitely moving towards the landing target.
حتماً يتحرك نحو هدف الهبوط.
Watch the whip of its tail as it does it. Look at that.
شاهدو حركة ذيله بينما يقوم بذلك
It's unbelievable.
لا يصدق.
So now we were really confused,
الآن أصبحنا حائرين تماما
because there are no reports of it gliding.
لأنه لا توجد أي تقارير عن تحليقه
So we went, "Oh my god, we have to go to the field,
فذهبنا "يا إلاهي، علينا الذهاب إلى الساحة
and see if it actually does this."
لنرى إذا كان يفعل ذلك في الواقع"ـ
Completely opposite of the way you'd see it on a nature film, of course.
بالطبع عكس الطريقة التي سترونها على برامج الطبيعة تماما
We wondered, "Do they actually glide in nature?"
تسائلنا "هل يحلقون في الواقع في الطبيعة"ـ
Well we went to the forests of Singapore and Southeast Asia.
فذهبنا إلى غابات سنغافورة وجنوب شرق آسيا
And the next video you see is the first time we've showed this.
والمقطع التالي نعرضه لأول مرة
This is the actual video -- not staged, a real research video --
هذا هو المقطع الفعلي، غير مفبرك، مقطع بحث حقيقي
of animal gliding down. There is a red trajectory line.
لحيوان يحلق نزولا -- هناك خط المسار بالأحمر
Look at the end to see the animal.
انظروا إلى النهاية لترو الحيوان
But then as it gets closer to the tree,
ولكن بينما يقترب من الشجرة
look at the close-up. And see if you can see it land.
شاهدوا التقريب. وحاولوا رؤيته وهو يهبط
So there it comes down. There is a gecko at the end of that trajectory line.
ها هو ينزل. هناك وزغة في نهاية خط المسار
You see it there? There? Watch it come down.
هل ترونه هناك؟ شاهدوه ينزل
Now watch up there and you can see the landing. Did you see it hit?
والآن شاهدو هناك ويمكنكم رؤية الهبوط. هل رأيتم الإرتطام؟
It actually uses its tail too,
إنه يستخدم ذيله كذلك
just like we saw in the lab.
تماما كما رأينا في المختبر
So now we can continue this mutualism
فالآن يمكننا إكمال هذا التعاون
by suggesting that they can make an active tail.
باقتراح صنع ذيل فعال
And here is the first active tail, in the robot,
وهذا أول ذيل فعال في روبوت
made by Boston Dynamics.
صنعوه في بوستن داينامكس
So to conclude, I think we need to build biomutualisms, like I showed,
في الختام، أعتقد أننا نحتاج إلى بناء تعاون بيولوجي، كما أوضحنا
that will increase the pace of basic discovery in their application.
والذي سيزيد من سرعة الاكتشافات الأساسية في تطبيقاتها
To do this though, we need to redesign education in a major way,
لفعل ذلك نحتاج إلى إعادة تصميم التعليم بطريقة جذرية
to balance depth with interdisciplinary communication,
لنوازن بين العمق والتفاعل بين العلوم
and explicitly train people how to contribute to, and benefit from other disciplines.
صراحة لتدريب الناس ليضيفوا ويستفيدوا من العلوم الأخرى.
And of course you need the organisms and the environment to do it.
وبالطبع نحتاج إلى الكائنات والبيئة لنقوم بذلك
That is, whether you care about security, search and rescue or health,
هذا، سواء أنت تهتم بالأمن، البحث والإنقاذ أو الصحة
we must preserve nature's designs,
فعلينا الحفاظ على تصاميم الطبيعة
otherwise these secrets will be lost forever.
وإلا ستضيع هذه الأسرار للأبد.
And from what I heard from our new president,
ومن ما سمعته من رئيسنا الجديد،
I'm very optimistic. Thank you.
أنا متفائل جدا. شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)